Oh, you got to become a like a robot
where you don't have emotions and that's
how you become a good trader. It's like
that's like saying you got to learn how
to not breathe, right? Like you can't do
that, right? So again, like you say,
your your emotions don't need to
disappear and they won't disappear,
right? But your and your processes need
to be stronger than your impulses,
right? So this is where understanding
your impulse, what that is,
understanding the emotion you're feeling
and why you're having that impulse. One,
you can build up resilience over time.
So it's not about eliminating your
emotions, about being aware of your
emotions and being aware of your
response and countering that and then
slowly over time you build up a
resilience to it and a better
understanding. And that's where the
awareness piece comes in, right? Like
really observing what you're feeling,
what you're doing, why you're doing what
you're doing, and then try to get to
those underlying issues and try to
either deal with them. Like a lot of
people, you know, they have trauma from
the past. They have all sorts of beliefs
from the past and those are going to
trigger them and they're going to
trigger behavior and until they actually
deal with them and understand them,
they're they're going to continue to
make those mistakes, right?
>> What would your trading look like if
capital wasn't the constraint? That's
the reality for most traders. It's not
skill holding them back. It's size.
Trade the pool changes that. Step into
the US equity markets with up to
$200,000 in buying power without
committing your own capital. Full access
to stocks and ETFs, long or short,
executed with the precision and freedom
serious traders expect. Your performance
is measured by one standard. Disciplined
risk management and consistent
execution. Meet that standard and you
operate at scale. No subscriptions, no
ongoing obligations, just a clear path
forward. For those ready to trade beyond
limitations, this is the next level.
Markets, speculation, [music]
and risk. This is the Chat with Traders
podcast.
>> [music]
>> All right, traders. Welcome to another
episode of Chat with Traders. My guest
today is Peter Robbins, a trader with
more than 50 years of experience
navigating the financial markets. Now,
Peter's journey spans multiple market
eras from a time when trading was driven
largely by fundamentals and high
commission costs to today's fastmoving
technologydriven environment. Over those
[clears throat] decades, he's
experienced the full spectrum, trading
full-time, part-time, making making
significant gains, taking meaningful
losses, and continuing to show up year
after year. Professionally, his
background includes corporate finance
and investments across the medical
technology and insurance industries, as
well as serving as a corporate
controller in the building industry. But
throughout it all, Peter has remained
just a constant passion for trading. His
style has evolved with the markets from
day trading futures, swing trading
stocks and options to longerterm
position trading and ETFs that reflects
both adaptability and longevity in a
game where most do not last. Today,
Peter is dedicated to mentoring traders
and sharing the lessons he's learned
across five decades in the markets. With
an online following of over 100,000
people, he continues to emphasize not
just strategy, but mindset, discipline,
and self-awareness required to survive
and succeed in trading. In this episode,
we're going to explore what's changed in
trading over the those last 50 years,
what hasn't changed, and the deeper
truths Peter has uncovered about risk
discipline in the internal battle every
trader faces. Please enjoy my
conversation now with Peter Robbins.
Peter, thank you so much for joining
Chat with Traders.
>> Thank you so much, Kevin. That was quite
the introduction. It makes me feel old.
[laughter]
>> Well, it's been the trader journey, just
like the book that you just wrote and
came out with. Read it over the weekend.
And what a great what what a great book,
The Trader Journey. So, let's rewind a
little bit and go through Peter's
trading journey 50 years ago, back in
the 70s. What was it like now versus the
then versus now?
>> Well, again, if you if you think about
it, what what was the 70s like, right?
No computers, no internet, no charting.
I think they had charting back then, but
they would come out once a month or
something. Someone would do charts and
and send it out as a subscription. There
was many brokerage firms, a lot of small
boutique brokerage firms before the
consolidation.
And like you mentioned in the
introduction, high commissions. So for
someone with a small account, you're
basically trading in order to uh pay the
commissions.
And it also it also made you sort of
trade a certain methodology that may or
may not be right for you, but you know,
you weren't able like as opposed to
today, right, where zero or very low
commissions, instant access almost like
you can open an account, you can start
trading immediately and you know, so all
of the risk, all of the changes there.
how you can you can day trade, you can
swing trade, you can not worry too much
about commissions, you can get in and
out of a trade if you're wrong. And so
it it offers a lot of advantages, but
there's also additional risk involved,
right? There's a temptation to
overtrade. There's a you know temptation
to want to trade a certain style like
everyone wants to day trade it seems,
but a lot of people aren't cut out to
day trade. So a lot of people are drawn
there only be because the the
environment allows you to but uh you
know again it's sort of a gift and a
trap at the same time right depending on
what your situation is. So
>> right I remember reading in your book
too where you would say you would you
may have a profitable trader from back
then but they're net negative because of
how expensive it was to trade back then.
>> Yeah. Unless you had a large account. I
mean, think about it. Nowadays, people
have $500 in their account they can
trade. Uh, you know,
>> whereas back then in an in-n-out
commission might be $50 or more, might
even be a $100. So, if you have only a
$500 account, it's literally you it's
almost impossible to make money, right?
And uh
>> so,
>> what what was your introduction like?
What was it about trading that just
hooked Peter immediately to it?
>> Yeah. But when you say five decades, you
got to you got to think how old was I
when I started trading. So I was
literally 15 years old when I started
trading. [laughter]
I had to get my parents to open an
account for me. Me and a buddy from uh
school, we were interested in business.
We were interested in trading just like
most people today, right? They're
interested because they want to make
money. Let's face it, right? That's
that's what draws people to it. And we
were getting ready to go to university
looking for a way to make some extra
money. And again, like most traders
today, we had no clue what we were
doing. [laughter] So, but that's where,
right, you get it, you jump in. What do
they say? It's like building a plane
when it's when it's flying, right? So,
you you jump in, you're learning the
lessons and and then you're adapting and
changing as you go. And a lot of that
would have to been you know well we
can't really trade until we have more
money or you know and then again slowly
luckily fairly quickly things changed
where the internet came out computers
came out all sorts of tools and things
so obviously uh you know we're able to
quickly adapt to that environment and uh
trade accordingly. Right.
>> So you said that it was more
fundamentally driven back then and then
it eventually changed to technicals. Are
you able to kind of graph that out over
the years? Uh where you know we have
different you have this fundamental
analysis, technical analysis, trader
analysis. How has that shifted over all
these years?
>> Yeah. So, so back then and and it's not
only the 70s but probably the 80s and
even nowadays there's a lot of people
that feel technical analysis is kind of
you know woo woo it's doesn't it's not
really doesn't really work or whatever,
right? that it's become more and more uh
acceptable and become more and more
available to people, right? Like think
back then there literally was no
charting capabilities. There was there
were some guys in the brokerage firms
that would draw charts by hand, but you
can imagine how they were considered,
right? They were like, "Okay, that's
that crazy guy in the corner over there
with his charts, right?" So then
eventually you know and when you think
when you look back to the old classic
books on investing a lot of them are
value investing books and then there was
some technical analysis books right but
again unless you had the capabilities to
do it um it it made it very hard to to
trade accordingly right so and then like
I say rap fairly rapidly with the advent
of the PC and computer technology then
the tools started to come out like you
you know, all the tools that people are
using today, right? And then obviously
as it became more and more advanced as
far as technologically
uh sizes of computers, speed, etc. You
now you can you can do everything from
AI trading to, you know, trading ticks,
right? So it's
>> over all the years, what what
instruments have you traded? You've tra
have you traded everything? Yeah, I
think at at some point or other I've
pretty much traded most instruments from
you know again started off I'm from
Canada so it as a young child you know
it's it's a re resource-based market as
you know in Canada everyone trades penny
stocks you know that's why you're in it
for the to make the big money on the on
the penny stocks just like a lot of
traders nowadays are also attracted to
high volatile you know instruments in
order to make money fast right so you So
traded that and then got more into just
stocks with a more of a longer term
focus. And when you were saying
fundamentally driven, like I say, a lot
of the information was, you know,
information on fundamentals of a
company. But I give you an example for a
brokerage firm that would, you know,
provide information to their clients.
They would have a newsletter come out
every two weeks. [laughter]
So So that's another big difference,
right? Like and now everything is
instantaneous information, right? like
you just you can go online and people
are recommending things it's as it's
live right as things are happening the
market's changing back then you know you
didn't again the stock mo stock market
itself was open cry you know it was it
was all manual it was all uh you know it
was very slow right you had to call your
broker the broker had to call the floor
the floor had to do the trade uh so that
takes a long time right so so you're not
in it to to you know get get an a penny
difference in a bid and ask or big big
spreads big slow slow process right um
but yeah so over time yeah traded
futures traded commodities traded
options traded stocks and then not only
different instruments but also different
styles and and uh adapted styles
depending on my personal situation and
and uh
>> and where where do you land today
position trading is what I was reading
in the book right you do a lot more just
position trading, right?
>> Yeah. Well, I'm retired now, so I mean I
I don't I I always say day trading,
first of all, I day trading is a tough
thing to do, but I'm the odd time I
might day trade just when things are
really volatile and I have a have some
free time, but I'm retired, right? I
want to spend my time doing more doing
other things in trading. A lot of people
that do trade, they they're fixated on
it and they're almost addicted to it,
right? But it's also the ability to
stand back, take a longer term
perspective. um and realize that chances
are especially depending on your your
own personality that might be more
successful for you anyways, right? So
that's where I've sort of landed. I
trade mainly US stocks right now. Again,
typical US stocks, leaders in the
industry, leaders in the market and uh
you know, that's what that's my focus
pretty much.
>> So you've experienced both making a lot,
losing a lot through all of that. What
like what do you think has led to the
longevity? because that's where a lot of
traders fall off, right? They they just
don't they don't last because this the
market, as you know, is a mirror. It's a
mirror on our flaws and then traders
often times will say, you know, this is
this is more than I can handle. I don't
want I don't want to come face to face
with my uh with my flaws. So, I I have a
idea from reading your book, you know,
you used to one word that was just
thematic, if you will, in your book that
just kept coming up and up is passion.
Passion. So, but why do what what led to
the longevity? Why do you think most
traders quit? Is it that passion or is
it something else?
>> Well, I think and again getting into the
trading business and I call it business
on purpose. But getting into trading,
first of all, like anything, if you want
to learn to trade, you should you
probably need a passion. Just like
whether you're going to learn to play
golf or learn to play an instrument or
become a lawyer or a doctor, whatever,
you need a p you need to you need to
have a passion for it, right?
Unfortunately, a lot of traders, they
they get into trading not because
they're necessarily tra passionate about
trading. They're passionate about making
money, right? And they come with
unrealistic expectations. They come
with, you know, sort of a the wrong
approach, right? It's like I just want
to make quick money easily. And then
once they get in there, they realize
quickly that oh, number one, it's not
easy. It's a very difficult business.
And those that stick around, they either
find that they can learn and adapt and
are they're resilient, they learn
quickly, and they adapt accordingly. Um,
and and unless you do that, you're gone,
right? And also, they find out whether
or not they h have the real passion. And
if they do, they're liable to stick
around longer. And uh you know they
learn qu they learn quickly but uh yeah
>> I've heard it like go ahead
>> they have a skill like they they realize
like anything else trading isn't just
anyone can do it right as much as all of
the stuff you see online out there it's
like anyone can do it one weekend course
you'll become an expert trader just
follow my methodology and you'll become
rich overnight all of these things
people are are attracted to the trading
for all the wrong reasons right And but
once you get into it, either you develop
the skills and you have the skills and
you have the interest or you don't,
right? And if you don't, you're you're
going to you're going to quit. Just like
if if you're uh when you're growing up,
if your dad wants you to play hockey and
you get skates on and a hockey stick and
you go out there and you just hate it
and you're just no good at it, right?
It's like you're not going to stick
around, right? something I've heard put
like this where traders they
underestimate the amount of work that's
going to take and then they overestimate
the profit the profits u and so yeah
that they come into it with the wrong
mindset so something that I love about
you Peter is uh you speak hard truths
which you were just right right now in
fact that saying where you like oh I can
make the $400 a day you had you had
written about this this hard truth which
again these hard truths I want to get
into because it's not a very popular
conversation to speak hard truths as
you're aware now. It may be a profitable
approach but not necessarily popular.
That I mean that there's a difference
there, right? So I think traders they
will benefit a lot in hearing a lot of
these hard truths like the one you were
just alluding to which I I read and it's
so true. You'll see the gurus they say
look all you need to do is make the $400
a day and that's a h 100,000 a year. But
the problem is that you noted Peter is
most traders are going to start likely
with 10,000 or less in their account.
And so if you have 10,000, you're making
400 a day. That's a,000% year-over-year
return as you as you pointed out. So
people have those unrealistic
expectations
uh on trading. Is that what you've seen
over the years? Are you ready to get
serious about options trading? Then join
Tasty Trade, Investopedia's best
platform for options trading 2026.
Stocks, options, futures, and more.
Tasty Trade has everything you trade all
in one platform. Get low commissions,
including a $10 cap per leg on options
trades, so you can keep more of what you
earn. Tasty Trade is packed with
advanced charting tools, back testing, a
pre-built strategy selector, and more
features to help you trade smarter.
Manage your positions with speed and
precision using active trader mode,
one-click trading, and smart order
tracking. Plus, Tasty Trade stellar
trade desk team offers live support
during trading hours if you need it.
Join Tasty Trade today and earn a double
commission rebate up to $3,000 total on
your stock and ETF option trades for 30
days. Visit tastyrade.com/hat
for more info. All applicable regulatory
exchange and clearing fees still apply.
Options involves risk and are not
suitable for all investors. Learn more
about Tasty Trade promo terms and
conditions at tastyrade.com/double.
Offer expires May 31st, 2026. Tasty
Trade Incorporated is a registered
broker dealer and member of FINRA NFA
and SIPC.
>> Yeah. Well, again, when when they start
trading, um, and let's let's look at
sort of what what people are sold about
trading, right? So, so to your point,
hard truths are not things people want
to hear, but they should hear, right?
>> Yeah.
>> And but what they want to hear and what
they get excited about are all these,
you know, false claims, right? That you
can make lots of money, trading's easy,
you don't doesn't take long to learn it,
etc., etc., right? But and that's part
of the reason why I wrote the book and
what and I know you you mentioned I have
a uh following on X at at that you know
again I wasn't expecting to get a
following because I was giving out the
hard truths right but obviously there is
group of people that recognize that
these truths are real and they want to
approach trading like a business and
they want to approach it correctly and
that's what's exciting to me right is
that okay there is this group and
chances are they're the ones that are
going to succeed and they're going to be
around longer. Um, so but it's not it's
not a sexy cell, right? It's not a it's
it's not from my perspective I you know
even selling this book right there's
probably a lot harder than someone
saying follow this book this is my
methodology you can copy it and you can
make tons of money right as opposed to
me saying here's a book that will teach
you about the business of trading it'll
give you a foundation it'll show you all
the things that are are real
>> you know who wants to who wants to hear
that
>> you you you could have named it how to
make $100,000 with with a a $500
[laughter] I'm probably sold a lot more.
But yeah, I love it. The Yeah, the hard
the hard truths. And you're right. Like
you have you have a great audience, a
great I mean a really large 133 plus
thousand people that uh that want to
hear these hard truths. You you have
real traders. These are these have to be
real traders. So you have a great
audience there. So one thing I noted uh
as well uh from your journey Peter's
journey is the aha moment you've spoken
about. So traders experience these aha
moments over their journeys and and one
that you experienced uh you said was a
big turning point for you was just
learning how to take small losses along
the way. Can you take us back to when
that really clicked for you? Yeah. And
like I say, as you're learning to trade,
especially if you don't have like for me
personally, I didn't have anyone in my
family or any friends that were traders.
So, this was a learning on my own. And
and back when there wasn't a lot of, you
know, traders or mentors out there. So,
when you're when you're trading, you
quickly uh you know, you get you get
hurt, right? You get you lose money. And
every time you lose money or you and
again that's you either learn a lesson
or you continue to repeat it until
you're either broke or you give up,
right? But the idea that these aha
moments where every time that you are
trading and you find yourself doing a
certain behavior over and over again
that's self-destructive or is hurting
your account and unless you step back
and say okay this isn't working I need
to change. uh you know that's that
that's what I me meant by these aha
moments right and the the big one and
let's face it if you look at trading
from a mathematical perspective you know
it's really simple right you have
percentage wins percentage losses
average win average loss and you have
your and and it multiplies out right and
and then that's either you have a
positive expectancy or you're losing
money right depending on what those
stats are and one of the big aha moments
you learn quickly is that if you take
big losses And I know a lot of the
trading books they show that right like
if you lose 50% then you need a 100%
return in order to get back to your
break even. Um so uh that's when that
clicks it's like okay you're you become
more comfortable taking those small
losses because you realize you can have
10 losses instead of one and you have
when you do those 10 trades you have a
higher probability of making money.
Right. So,
>> do you think that traders have to go
through this pain or these draw downs to
truly learn that lesson? Because I've
heard it put this this way, Peter, which
I, you know, I'm on the fence. I'm
curious to hear what your thoughts are
over 50 years. Some traders will say,
"Look, if you don't have to crash a
plane to learn how to fly, but I will
say in trading, from what I've seen in
the a lot shorter amount of time than
your experiences, traders, it when they
go through those draw downs, it gets
seared into their memory to the point
where they have crashed that plane and
it's not going to happen again." So, I
I've seen where traders do in the draw
downs really learn more a lot more and
quicker than otherwise. But what what
are your thoughts on that? What's your
experience? Yeah. Well, again, it
depends like let's say for example, if
we're talking about mentorships as an
example, right? If someone's there to
help you, hold your hand, teach you. Um,
then obviously it helps they help you
see the blind spots, they help avoid
repeated mistakes, at least they can
tell you those things, right? The
question is whether and even like my
book, right? I I I lay out exactly what
you can do in order to, you know, see
the mistakes you're going to make, see
these things in advance. But whether you
have the ability to absorb that
knowledge and
adapt to it, and a good one, a good
example is let's say someone tells you,
you know, all of these great traders,
they've all lost and it burned an
account at one point in time or another.
But chances are, why did they do that,
right? And it was either because they
took on too much risk or they they made
emotional decision or they got caught up
in they caught up in the emotional side
of business and ma and did behavior that
they knew was wrong and shouldn't have
done right now. So the question then
becomes can you as an individual if
you've got the right
education and the right sort of
knowledge and uh can you make those
changes before you have to take take
that suffering. A good example, like you
say, is taking small losses, right?
Everyone knows that you need to take
small losses in order to survive here.
Yeah. If you take a big loss, it's going
to reinforce that that lesson, but but
and often times a lot of people will
make that mistake and and have to
relearn it over and over again, right?
And this is where it comes back more to
the psychological side of trading,
right? So the strategy with a positive
expectation and the rules that you need
to follow, that's sort of the easy part,
right? Everyone there's lots of
methodologies out there that people can
can trade, but it's their your ability
to trade it that really gives you the
edge, right? So or or makes the edge
possible. And if you're
uh like what happens is you get
triggered for some reason, you you have
an emotional response and then you have
a behavior according to that, right? And
then you realize, oh man, I've I
shouldn't have done that. So that's
where again journaling, tracking your
trades, understanding your your emotion
at the time that you're doing these
things and the behavior that comes out
of it helps to you to build up that
resilience over time, right? understand
that reaction and then um you know as
you're about like I know for myself
let's say in the past where the market
was crashing I would get really excited
and start buying puts and and just at
the right just at the time that the
market's bottoming out right because
again that's the emotional response
people are scared they and and think
they can make money on the downside um
and now I realize okay I'm feeling that
chances are that's a a sentiment signal
to me that Okay, instead of getting
short, maybe now it's time to get long
because you've made this mistake before
and look at and being able to step back
and look at the market. Where are we in
the market? What's really going on and
be able to um feel feel your emotions
and the behavior you want to do and then
put it stop it, right? And then do do
what you know.
>> Oh man,
>> that is excellent. I mean, so what
you're alluding to is over 50 years, the
emotions may not necessarily go away,
but you learn how to respond to them.
You don't you don't necessarily act,
right? Like if you if you have the fear
of missing a move, you don't have to act
on that. In fact, you can act uh in the
contrary uh against the 90% of traders.
Is that what you're saying? So the
emotions maybe because some traders
think the emotions will subside over the
years but over 50 years are you saying
so the emotions are still present you've
just learn how to act on them?
>> Yeah. Well again we're all humans right
so you're going to when you're in and
the other thing you got to recognize
we're our money's at risk. This is a
very emotional thing right people and
money people have a lot of beliefs about
money. They have a lot of you know it's
crit critical in society right I mean
having money is is very important to
survive but a lot of people are told oh
you got to become a like a robot where
you don't have emotions and that's how
you become a good trader it's like
that's like saying okay you you got to
learn how to not breathe right
you can't do that right so again like
you say your your emotions don't need to
disappear and they won't disappear right
but your and your processes need to be
stronger than your impulses, right? So,
this is where understanding your
impulse, what that is, understanding the
emotion you're feeling and why you're
having that impulse. One, you can build
up resilience over time. So, it's not
about eliminating your emotions, about
being aware of your emotions and being
aware of your response and countering
that. And then slow slowly over time,
you build up a a resilience to it and a
better understanding. And that's where
the awareness piece comes in, right?
like really observing what you're
feeling, what you're doing, why you're
doing what you're doing, [snorts] and
then try to get to those underlying
issues and try to either deal with them.
Like a lot of people, you know, they
have trauma from the past, they have all
sorts of beliefs from the past and they
it and that those are going to trigger
them and they're going to trigger
behavior and until they actually deal
with them and understand them, they're
they're going to continue to make those
mistakes, right? So, um, wow,
>> that's huge. Awareness. I mean, I love
it. Awareness. You got to just be so
self-aware in trading because again,
traders, uh, trading is a mirror. It's a
reflection. So, you have to be so fully
aware of really your mindset in the
moment. And that's something I want to
transition to here in a second. But you
had mentioned mentorship and how mentors
can help you in with your blind spots.
Now, I read that you had a mentor. His
name was Bill Williams. and who who kept
telling you, "Look, Peter, it you got to
want what the market wants. Don't want
what you want. Want what the market
wants. It's just printing objective
information and never try to pick a
fight with it." So, I I want to ask you
how that advice kind of shaped your
trading and also how important do you
think it is to have a mentor?
>> Yeah. So, again, that whole thing about
self-awareness, right? Knowing knowing
when you're trading the market versus
when you're trading your mood, right?
And want and Bill's saying like I say,
want what the market wants. It just
makes so much sense, right? People
people trade what they want and the
market is going to do what it wants and
unless you get aligned with it and you
know dance with the market, you're
you're going to be uh you're going to
lose money, right? So, the idea of u a
mentorship and I' I've had a number of
mentors over the years, right?
>> Wasn't just Bill. When I was in
university, there was a broker down the
street I would go to and chat with and
they they would he would give me
lessons. But Bill was the first one that
uh was a big one in the sense of he
taught a certain his methodology which
again a lot of people will get caught up
in that right but it wasn't also but he
also talked a lot about psychology right
and how to deal with these things. So,
um, it was it was great to me. I look at
the market now through a certain way of
looking at it that I didn't see before
him and I learned it quickly and made a
huge difference on on me that way,
right? So, again, find and the problem
right now these days is finding the
right mentor, right? Because there's so
many mentors out there that are not
really mentors.
>> They're what do they call them? Furu
furus, right? like the false gurus and
they're just claiming certain stats that
are just literally impossible if you
looked at it right and uh you know
hopefully people are so being able to
find a mentor one that's that's good and
and again it's I we look at two things
one is a mentor and one is a coach right
so there's two different things there
right a mentors are using people that
are trading their methodology and teach
you their methodology which is great but
a coach is are someone that would look
at all the different variables of
trading, help you adapt to fit fit you
more p personally. Um, so again, it's
probably having a coach and when you
think about it, what other profession or
you know, anything out there where
people are learning something new where
they don't have a manager, a coach, a a
mentor, right? Like in business, if you
want to become a a doctor, you know,
you're a residence and you're you're in
residence with other experienced doctors
teaching you how to do things, right? If
you're a golfer, you spend time with the
pros. If you're you know, again, on to
why trading people think they need to do
it on their own is is very strange,
right?
>> It's the freedom, right? And I know and
Mark Douglas talked about that a lot how
we you just you're always told from a
young age onward, you know, you gotta
you got to do this, you got to do that.
And now, oh, I have unlimited freedom
and flexibility to be who I want to be
kind of thing. And people fall prey to
that trap, right? And then they they get
they get sucked in, chewed up, and spit
out. So in your um this transitions
right into the next piece here, which is
trading as a business, you know, that's
what you emphasize. Traders should focus
on building a business. So let's get rid
of that freedom mindset where I can be
who I want to be and focus more on
building this business plan. And then
you say the money is a byproduct of
that. So you're focus focused first on
business, secondary money. Why do you
think traders get that backwards? Well,
again, most of them are attracted to
trading for the money and they don't
want they and and they they're
surrounded by all these unrealistic
expectations about, you know, what what
does it take, right? Um, so my whole
point is that, you know, trading is a
serious endeavor. It's a it's a serious
career and you need to take it
seriously, right? And and it's not just
pressing a button to buy and pressing a
button to sell. There's also it's just
like running just like running a small
business, right? Like there's
administration involved, there's
marketing involved. Like there's all
these you buying something. And so
there's so many things to know and do.
There's journaling, there's tracking
your trades, there's doing your tax like
so when if you don't if you come at it
thinking of it as a business and and
recognizing all these components, then
hopefully you'll take it more seriously
and and not just dive in because that's
where people just dive in and and they
lose. So, a business has rules, they
have risk limits, they have routines,
they they review and and that part about
freedom, like it always kills me when I
see, you know, people trading on the
beach. Like, what does that even mean,
right? They're they're still doing
they're still working, right? They're
sitting there with their computer and
they're thinking. It's not like they're
they're just dreaming about the beach.
They're like trading, right? So, it's
this whole idea of freedom. And in fact,
it's the opposite of freedom, right?
There's lots of things you need to
control. There's lots of things you need
to manage. [snorts] and freedom, you
know.
>> Yeah, you said it. It's the edge, which
is not just having that positive
expectancy uh to it, but also having
just the discipline to execute it. Why?
Why is that discipline component just
the the harder part? Cuz it it seems
like, you know, the edge, oh, I have an
edge. I have an edge. There's a positive
EV here. But why do you think that the
discipline to execute on it is that hard
part?
>> Well, I think that is that emotional
side of things, right? The ability to
execute. you know, most failures are
execution failures, not lack of
intelligence or lack of a of a strategy.
It's they just don't have that emotional
resilience to be able to trade it uh
consistently and effectively, right? So,
so that's where again building up
understanding, awareness, understanding
why you're doing what you're doing and
then discipline can be built over time,
right? It's it's not something where you
can just say, are you going to be
disciplined now? Right? First of all,
you need a strategy. You need to
document it. You need to understand the
rules. Exactly. you need to, you know,
have then you need to build good habits,
right? Which is is the discipline,
right? It's like, okay, in the morning
I'm going to do this and that this is my
checklist. This is what I after the day
is over, this is how I'm going to review
my trades. This is what I'm going to do
this. And as you the more you and that's
work that people don't talk about.
Again, that's one of those hard truths,
right? No one no one wants to tell you
you're running a business here, right?
It's like, I thought I just had to buy
and you guys are the Bitcoin was going
to go to the moon and I was going to be
read gonna be rich, right? It's like
Yeah. And it it's funny, right? Because
even when you when you hear about uh the
most successful traders out there that
people are aware of and they talk about
their returns, like the the true
traders, you know, they have double
digit returns in a year, right? And
they're and they consider themselves
successful. And why you think you can
make a thousand% return and without any
experience or or knowledge or
discipline, then it's it's [snorts] just
funny, right? unrealistic expectations.
Yeah. Yeah. So, I mean, you had you you
said that having a a mentor versus a
coach, a mentor is there to kind of show
you their their system and strategy. So,
if if let's say a trader, they just
don't they don't know their system yet.
You talk about how your personality
really needs to be congruent with the
strategy you're trading. So, what
happens when there's a mismatch? Maybe
you're learning from a mentor and that
their strategy just doesn't work for
you. So how can someone go about finding
their system and edge?
>> Yeah. Well, I think first of all it's
really important to study different
traders and different meth
methodologies, right? I know for myself
when I read uh Bill Williams book it
automatically it was like okay this is
this makes sense to me and this is
exciting right? Um, and just like
likewise, some people are going to read
about Can Slim or they're going to read
about value investing or they're gonna
like and that and that resonates with
them, right? Like let's say you're an
accountant and you really love analyzing
balance sheets and P&Ls, you know, you
might be more geared towards value
fundamental trading or fundamental
investing as opposed to someone that's
really analytical and loves as a visual
learner and they they love the technical
side of things, right? But a lot of
people, they jump into trading into a
style without ever considering whether
or not it's right for them, right? And
it must fit your temperament. It must
fit your schedule. Like a lot of people
want to day trade and they have
full-time jobs. Like it's just literally
impossible, right? And then the whole
thing about stress and money management,
right? Like how much stress can you
take? There's some people that love
going all in and they're they they
they're willing to take big risks and
they can take it handle a draw down and
there's other people that can't even
handle a 10% draw down without you know
having an emotional breakdown. So
anyway, so that's the first thing I
always do is like study a bunch of
trading methodologies
and then find something that resonates
with you and it it doesn't have to be
exact, right? Like I I I always say an
example would be like an artist, right?
So a lot of people study the masters,
right? They look at Monet, they look at
Gogan, they look at uh, you know,
whoever, and they they practice their
their styles until they they sort of
figure out they blend something together
that that really works for them and it's
their own style, right? And it's the
same thing with trading. Review a bunch
of trading methodologies, try some, and
you'll see like, no, this isn't making
me feel good. I've seen so many people
that are day traders that that it
doesn't they shouldn't be day trading um
because they're they're because of their
personality and their stuff. And if you
have a mismatch like why it's important
if you're if you're not aligned with
your strategy then you're going to make
all those mistakes, right? because and
and that's a f sort of a starting point
is that if a lot of people they might
even have you know discipline and be
able to do things but if they're if
they're not aligned to their strategy
they it still can then trigger different
things that just they're just not able
to to manage it right um so and again
the best strategy is one that you can
follow when you're uncomfortable and
when you're you know when times are
tough
>> I love that I love that yeah it's uh
it's so important to define that time
frame. And you said even uh in this
interview that right now you're working
on a a longer term time frame uh versus
short-term. But I I cracked up when I
was reading your book. You said you some
people think they're on a short time
frame, they'll take a scalp, but then
they end up turning to the long-term
investor. Now they're working a long
time frame. So, but that's why it's so
important, right, to define that prior
to ever taking the train.
>> Yeah. and sticking to it. Right? So
that's and again one of the one of the
problems with with traders or human
nature is that we want to be right.
Right? So the idea is so a lot of people
they start trading and again with all
the misinformation and and uh out there
that they think every trade works for
some bizarre reason, right? Again we all
know that you know a good trader might
have a 55% win rate. So that means you
know 45% of their trades are going to be
losses and hopefully small losses right.
So, um, yeah, it's so having that so
having that need for it to be right and
need to have control where where it's an
uncontrollable environment causes a lot
of people to put on a trade and then as
as long as they don't close a trade,
they they consider it still, well, I
haven't lost. I haven't I'm not wrong
yet, right? It'll come back and I'll
I'll make money eventually and they're
sitting there with a bunch of stocks
they've held for 20 years because
[laughter]
they never came back, right? It's only a
loss if it's realized, right? That's
what they're thinking.
>> So, we'll get back to the so strategy
versus the discipline to follow it.
You've said one of the biggest risks in
trading is just the trader's emotional
state. Uh what are routines or habits
that traders can take to help really
manage the emotional state? Doesn't your
portfolio deserve the best? Then join
Tasty Trade, Investopedia's best
platform for options trading 2026. Trade
smarter with advanced charting tools,
back testing, a pre-built strategy
selector, and more features. Join Tasty
Trade today and earn a double commission
rebate up to $3,000 total on your stock
and ETF option trades for 30 days. Visit
tastyrade.com/hat
for more info. All applicable
regulatory, exchange, and clearing fees
still apply. Options involve risks and
are not suitable for all investors.
Learn more about Tasty Trade promo terms
and conditions at tastyrade.com/double.
Offer expires May 31st, 2026. Tasty
Trade Incorporated is a registered
broker, dealer, and member of FINRA,
NFA, and SIPC.
>> Yeah. So, I think the first thing, and
that's what we talked about, awareness,
right? The first thing is to be aware of
what is actually happening to you,
right? So, a lot of people just like
they'll trade like crazy during the day
and they'll they'll end up losing money
on the day and if you ask them like what
did you do? It's like they just it's
like oh my god I was just you know
caught up in in the emotional side and
just doing things that and then if they
review their trades at the end of the
day and see okay oh my god why did I
even enter there like it's it doesn't
even make sense right so understand
>> but you say you say don't just journal
the trades but you say journal your
emotional awareness during the trades as
well right
>> right and that's and and again as you
start to become aware
then it it may not even be journaling,
but even talking to yourself, right?
Like, oh my god,
>> I'm I'm I know this is a FOMO trade,
right? And I know I shouldn't be doing
that. And and you know, so you can start
to to name the emotions you're having
and understand where you're wanting to
go.
>> And as you build up that knowledge and
understand those behaviors that you have
and the triggers that you have, then
over time, you can start to recognize
them and and adjust accordingly. And
then but again having also routines that
help you re reduce the impact of those
triggers and and the emotions you're
having right so that's where you know
again the journaling and and some people
need to actually go to therapy right
like the best thing some things if you
some beliefs some you know the way you
were brought up or traumas you might
have like literally you will never be a
successful trader unless you address
those things right because you're always
going to be triggered and have those
those that's sort of or not not
necessarily extremes. A lot of traders
when you sit down and not talk to them,
you know, what are they why do what are
they trying to prove, right? They're
trying to make their their parents feel
good or they're trying like there's all
these uh you know, subtle, you know,
things that happen in their past that
that are driving their behavior, right?
And really spending the time to address
those and understand them and and then
over time you start to, you know, you
you're in a position where you build
resilience. You can, and like I said
before, you can, you know, okay, I'm
feeling this and I know why I'm feeling
this, but and I'm not going to let this
drive my behavior, right?
>> Yeah, that's really
>> segue into that uh beliefs and just that
internal dialogue. It's really profound
what what you said in the book where you
say, you know, we're not trading the
market, we're trading our beliefs about
the market. So can you give us some
examples of some limiting beliefs that
traders commonly have?
>> Yeah. And it's not just trading your
beliefs about the market. It's trading
your beliefs that you have yourself.
Right. So for example, one some common
limiting ones might be you have to work
hard in order to make money. Right?
>> And that's that's where a lot of people
gets get uh caught up in day trading,
right? they feel like they need to be at
their screen eight hours a day and they
need to be making decisions and they
need to do this and that and they think
that's the only way I'm going to make
lots of money, right? As opposed to if
they just step back and look at their
trades and say, you know, if I had have
just held on to that trade for a week, I
would have made five times that I did on
that scalp or that that short-term day
trade. And so that's a that's an example
of a a limiting belief, right? Um you
know another one common is that you know
a lot of people have feel there's some
people feel there's unlimited
opportunities and some people feel
there's limited opportunities right so
if you come to the market with limited
that limitation mind mindset then you're
going to miss opportunities you're not
going to and you're going to be scared
to take take things or you're waiting
for the right the perfect trade or
whatever right but um you know again a
mindset of abundance and opportunity
gives you a
approach to the market, right?
>> How do traders take that limiting belief
then and say, "Look, let's turn this
into an empowering belief that you
discussed. How how do they go about
doing that?"
>> And this isn't just about trading. This
is just about life, right? And that
there's so many people that go through
life with a very negative mindset,
right, about themselves. If you if they
if you listened like humans, they have
feelings, they have emotions, they have
perceptions. And if if you're listening
and they have thoughts, right? And these
thoughts come to your come to you
through dialogue with yourself, right?
[snorts] So it's there's if you listen
to your self-t talk and you listen to
the dialogues you're having and again
whether that's just generally in life or
with regard to trading like in trading,
you might be saying, "Oh, you put it
this is another stupid trade. Why'd you
do this? You're an idiot. You don't know
how to trade. You got to get out of this
business." Whatever. So if there if a
lot of people talk to themselves like
they would never talk to anyone else
[laughter] like they they just very very
negative and self-deprecating. So thing
is to start to again comes back to this
awareness right and this is where you
get into stuff like meditation and
mindfulness and some pe some traders
might want to investigate that and and
go down those routes but the idea is
that yeah start to recognize when you're
having negative selft talk and replace
it with positive selft talk right like
um you know and and a lot of these are
also about your rules right like in
order to be a successful trader I need
to do this this this and this and remind
yourself of that right and if you're
doing something And that's not it's like
okay don't beat yourself up about it and
be negative to say okay I I made that
mistake I I acknowledge that you know
this is something that is because of
this and I'm going to be care I'm not
going to let it happen again right so
>> yeah yeah you emphasize that where
traders they they beat themselves
they got to they got to beat themselves
not necessarily the market uh and but
traders they sabotage themselves even if
they have an edge they sabotage
themselves because they're trying to
beat the market rather than look, you
got to look inwardly and and you got to
beat yourself and focus on those
empowering beliefs. And uh one of those
that you mentioned is really with your
winners trying to maximize those. It's
one thing that I've been trying to work
on improve on here recently too is that
you just when you have winners and
they're trending in your favor, you
suggest, hey, maybe add to the winner
instead of cutting it, instead of taking
profits early. How important do you
think it is for the long-term success to
really start, you know, adding to your
winners and trying to maximize those?
>> Yeah. Well, it's not necessarily again
the style of trading that you do depends
on what the market environment is,
right? So, there's a time to add to
winners when we're in a strongly
trending market and there's a time to
take your profits sooner. If we we step
back for a sec though, the idea of
taking not taking losses soon enough and
taking profits too soon, those are two
common behaviors that destroy accounts
and both of them are driven by needing
to be right. Right? So that that we
talked about, right? So you're holding
on to the losers because you don't want
to admit that you're wrong and you're
holding getting out of profits early
because oh, I've got to win right there.
Pat pat yourself on the back. You got a
winning trade. the idea of holding
longer and again this is can come out
when you analyze your trades like look
at your trades and then two weeks later
look at that same trade and see how it
would have panned out if you hel had
held it longer right and these are
things that will okay because you need
to convince yourself that that's the
right behavior um but that idea of
holding longer or adding so again like
if you look at the markets for the last
you know whatever four or five months
they've been just volatile not trending
>> all right So adding to winners probably
would have cost you a lot of money,
right? Because it's one day it's up,
next day it's down. One day it's up, one
next day it's down. So adding adding to
a winner would have been the complete
opposite approach and not taking profit
sooner would have also been the wrong
approach. So this is that idea of
stepping back and being not only being
aligned with your strategy, but having a
strategy that's aligned with the market,
right? And that's where again that takes
a long time to develop and a mindset
that people coming into trading don't
necessarily have, right? They're like,
"Oh, this is this is this is a strategy
I got to follow forever and it's going
to make me money." It's like, "No,
there's going to come a time where it's
not working because the environment
doesn't allow it, and you better change
or step aside until the market uh is
more
>> get rid of that ego. Get rid of that
ego, as you say, and the bias and don't
self- sabotage." Yeah. Traders often
times will get they get hopeful when
we're we're in the red and then get
fearful when we're in the green and then
end up you know self-sabotaging as you
say where we got to beat ourselves as
Peter Robbins says traders you got to we
got to beat ourselves not necessarily
think about oh we got to beat the market
uh so that passion that you've talked
about the passion being essential in
trading it's like it seems like it's the
the bloodstream really of the
sustainability of this journey the
trader journey which is your book. Uh
there's there's so much to learn there.
I mean do do you do you agree that you
think passion ultimately will go full
circle here is what's going to drive
people to that next level and keep you
in a sustainable journey for 50 years.
What I mean what's kept you engaged and
still learning even to this day?
>> Yeah definitely passion. You got to have
a love for for the business and uh you
know again a lot of people are driven to
that or they they they
confuse passion with um the need to make
money right so separating those things.
So you know you got to like trading
right you got to like analyzing stocks
you got to like looking at charts you
got to like like if you don't like it
you're not going to do it. And I think a
lot of people are you know again there's
a mis can be a misconception right like
a lot of people are looking for say the
holy grail. So if you're looking for the
holy grail at some point you're going to
realize there is no holy grail and
either you give up or you or you start
to you know you are passionate about
trading as a trade trader not as a
trying to find this holy grail or trying
to find the you know the pot of gold at
the end of the rainbow right and that's
where a lot of people are driven by that
greed uh and that's you know it's not
going to sustain you right because
you're going to keep like I' I've known
traders that just keep pouring money
into their accounts and pouring money
into their accounts and keep losing
losing losing and no matter what it's
like and they're driven not by the
passion to learn to trade and they're
they're not learning lessons and they're
repeating the same mistakes over and
over again. They're just think they're
just waiting for that one trade that's
going to make them the money, right? And
if they actually step back and looked at
how realistic that is depending on what
you trade like it's it's impossible to
happen, right? You'll never make up all
those losses or what they end up doing
is they keep on taking more and more
risk, more and more risk and until maybe
they'll luck out and have a have a good
trade, but chances are they've lost
more. Martale approach.
>> Martinale.
>> Yeah. People keep doubling their size
and Yeah. Yeah. So again, it's it's
beating yourself really and and having a
love for the game and money being a
byproduct of that's what I'm hearing
from you.
>> Ever watch a stock rip and think I could
have nailed that if I had real capital.
The truth is many capable traders never
reach their potential. Not due to lack
of skill but lack of scale. Trade the
Pool was built to solve exactly that. A
firm designed for serious individuals
who want access to the US equity markets
with meaningful buying power up to
$200,000 without committing their own
capital. Get access to virtually every
stock and ETF. Go long or short freely
with the flexibility professional
traders expect. You're evaluated on one
thing, your ability to manage risk and
execute with consistency. Meet the
standard and you trade at scale. No
subscriptions, no ongoing commitments.
Whether you're still refining your
strategy, a trader with experience who
hasn't yet broken through, or a seasoned
professional simply looking for more
capital, trade the pool is built to meet
you where you are and take you that next
step further. The markets have evolved,
access has evolved. Now, so has the way
traders operate within them. Trade the
pool. So your book called The Trader
Journey. I mean it's do you do you
believe that the journey ever truly ends
or we're always we're always on a trader
journey?
>> Yeah. Well, I think same thing with any
other profession, right? As time changes
and look at me like you said from the
70s to now, think about all of those
changes that are happening. And even in
the last 6 months from an AI
perspective, what's happening from a
trading perspective, right? So, if
you're if you're not learning, you're
falling behind. And if you're not
adapting, you're falling behind. Um, and
plus that's what makes it exciting,
right? like this is seeing a new tool,
seeing like I love there's a lot of
young young guys out there that are
developing new tools that are, you know,
taking advantage of these, you know, new
technologies that it's exciting, right?
It's it's neat to see what they're doing
and and adapting. Um, so yeah, that's
part of the part of the fun and part of
the the the passion. Um, but yeah, you
need to you need to adapt. Think of it
like a shark. If you're not if they
don't swim, they die, right? So, you got
to keep you got to keep moving and uh
keep learning and keep adapting and and
uh
>> love it. Love it. So, Peter, if you
could give traders one truth, one hard
truth that you took decades to fully
understand, what would it be?
>> Again, I think all the things we've
talked about like there's no there's no
one thing per se, but I think anyone
listening who wants sort of a realistic
framework for trading, right? And this
is, you know, all of the lessons, right?
It's like how to treat trading as a
business, how to choose a style that
fits your personality, building rules
you can follow, and developing that
self-awareness and execute under
pressure. That's that's sort of the the
lessons I've learned and that's what the
you know, the trader journey is designed
to deliver, right? So that that idea of
it's not it's not and again trading
isn't it's hard, right? and and there's
lots of there's lots of pieces that
involved and commit to it, learn from it
and uh you know I guess one of the key
lessons is the importance of I when I
talk about a trader's edge right a lot
of people think oh what's my edge what's
my edge right it's like okay I'm going
to buy this setup the setup is my edge
right but the the setup is two pieces or
the edge the edge is two sides a coin
right one is a strategy that's has a
positive expectation and the the other
one that a lot of people ignore and
don't spend time on is your ability to
trade it right and that ability to
trade. It really comes down to that
awareness and making changes to you your
your psychology and your beliefs and all
of those things that are make make it
easier for you to adapt and and trade
profitably and consistently. Right. So,
>> well, Peter, this has been an incredible
conversation. There's so much wisdom
here over the last 50 years. I
appreciate you taking the time to share
the journey, lessons, perspective with
all of us traders. Like the video, leave
us a comment if you if you've enjoyed
his book um and enjoyed the
conversation. Now for those listening
where can they find you Peter and also
where can they find the book?
>> Right. So the book is I guess uh an
obvious place would be Amazon but I
think a lot of the other big book
sellers also have it available. Um and
then for myself I'm on X and my my uh
what do they call it? Your handler
whatever is PR Robbins. And uh I like I
say one of the things about X there's a
lot of negative things about social
media but the one interesting thing
about the trading community if you take
away sort of the the scammers and the
the the fake gurus or whatever there's a
really tight great community just like
this chat with traders like got tons of
great podcast tons of great people and
that thing about trading doesn't need to
be a solitary business solitary business
you there's lots of people out there
willing to help and willing to to
communicate with you And that's what I
love doing. I like to help new traders
or even experienced traders. I'm
available on X. I my DM's always open
and uh you know I have a real passion
for that as well, right? And that's part
of the motivation for writing the book,
right? Because I'm just I hate seeing
new traders or experienced traders
continue to lose money and not and have
all these unrealistic expectations. So,
I wanted just to provide something out
there that gives them a solid foundation
and hopefully get them started quicker
and on a on a better footing than just
listening to someone on social media and
losing money, right? I you know, people
have saved I've seen young people where
they saved up all their money from high
school, all the jobs they've had, and
[snorts] literally lose it all on their
first trade. And it's like if they just
had someone holding their hand a little
bit, they they might have avoided that,
right? So,
>> Peter, thank you so much for sharing
these hard truths and follow them.
traders, if you want to hear some more
hard truths on X. Thank you for coming
on Chat with Traders. It's been a real
pleasure having you on. Thank you,
Peter.
>> Thank you, Kevin.
>> You've reached the end of this episode
of Chat with Traders, but rest assured
there are more episodes loaded [music]
with real market insight and zero hype
on the way soon. So, to stay updated
[music] with each great new release,
subscribe to the podcast and we'd love
it if you'd leave a rating and review.
We'll catch you next time on Chat with
Traders.
>> [music]